Guide to the Anna Elsbree papers, 1788-1953.
Elsbree, Anna papers, 1788-1953.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Anna Elsbree papers, 1788-1953.
1600
Anna Elsbree.
4.5 cubic ft.
Correspondence, an autograph album, an account book, a recipe book, a photograph album, photographs, broadsides, pamphlets, and other materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes genealogical correspondence, 1922-53; mimeographed Elsbree family letters and other papers; letters and other papers of Jabez and Lewis Beers relating to the New Jerusalem Church of Danby, 1815-74, and to the Ithaca and Owego Turnpike Company, 1810-20; attendance records and other papers of the Tornado Hook and Ladder Company, No. 3, Ithaca, 1843-1928; notes and clippings on history of Ithaca and Tompkins County; commencement ball in New Haven; invitations; cemetery records from Tompkins County; autograph album, account and recipe book, and photograph album of Llewellyn Elsbree; many family and other photographs; broadsides and pamphlets; and much miscellaneous material on local history and genealogy.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes genealogical correspondence, 1922-53; mimeographed Elsbree family letters and other papers; letters and other papers of Jabez and Lewis Beers relating to the New Jerusalem Church of Danby, 1815-74, and to the Ithaca and Owego Turnpike Company, 1810-20; attendance records and other papers of the Tornado Hook and Ladder Company, No. 3, Ithaca, 1843-1928; notes and clippings on history of Ithaca and Tompkins County; commencement ball in New Haven; invitations; cemetery records from Tompkins County; autograph album, account and recipe book, and photograph album of Llewellyn Elsbree; many family and other photographs; broadsides and pamphlets; and much miscellaneous material on local history and genealogy.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Elsbree, Anna, collector.; Beers, Jabez.; Beers, Lewis.; Elsbree family.; Elsbree, Llewellyn.; Ithaca and Owego Turnpike Company.; New Jerusalem Church (Danby, N.Y.); Tornado Hook and Ladder Company, No. 3 (Ithaca, N.Y.)
Subjects:
Cemeteries--New York (State)--Tompkins County.; Fire departments.; Fire stations.; Toll roads--New York (State)
Places:
Danby (N.Y.); Ithaca (N.Y.); Tompkins County (N.Y.)--Genealogies.
Form and Genre Terms:
Accounts.; Autographs.; Genealogies.; Photographs.; Recipes.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Photograph album of Llewellyn Elsbree - members of Cornell '71-'75 and others, 1871-1875 (Box 1)
- Autograph album of Mary Belle Sherman, Galesburg, IIlinois, Mar. 11, 1873 (Box 1)
- Notebook - bibliography, Curtis-Elsbree genealogy A-L (Box 1)
- Notebook - genealogy Elsbree A-L (Box 1)
- Notebook - genealogy Elsbree M-Z (Box 1)
- Notebook - copy of mms. from Lewis Beers papers in Tompkins County Historical Rooms copied by Anna Elsbree (Box 1)
- Account book of amounts owed various people for services rendered apparently on farm, 1813 (Box 1)
- Notebook - genealogy A-K (Box 1)
- Notebook - notes on early settlers of Ithaca and miscellaneous genealogies (Box 1)
- Account book, recipe book, 1833-1846 (Box 1)
- Jabez and Lewis Beers: New Jerusalem Society of the County of Tioga Church, Danby (Tioga County) papers; Ithaca & Owego Turnpike items, 1788-1874 (Box 2)
  1788-1874, n.d.: bills, receipts and IOU's etc.; 1769-1849: Lewis Beers, president of Ithaca & Owego Turnpike Co.; physician and preacher, 1810-1820; 1788: Jabez Beers certified by Dr. Joseph Poor as unfit for military duty; 1815: May 30, announcement of election of trustees (recorded May 31); 1817, March 16, agreement "to associate in Church Order" signed by Lewis and Jabez Beers, Moses Tyler and others at Danby; 1817, March 23, adoption of 2 articles as "sole bonds of Church Association;" 1819, May 29, baptismal certificate
- Jabez and Lewis Beers: New Jerusalem Church papers; Ithaca & Owego Turnpike item, 1788-1874 (Box 2)
  1824, Dec. 20, New Jerusalem Society - announcement of annual meeting, signed by Elbert Curtis, Sec'y; 1822, April 21, Danby - copy of letter "Dear Sister" on religion and work of the society, unsigned (Jabez Beers?); 1822, May 21, Danby, copy of letter sent to Annual Convention, Philadelphia regarding "present unhappy division of sentiments which prevail respecting the pastoral relation of the Minister to his Society;" 1824, Jan. 10, record of resolution to build church and to start a subscription; 1825, Jan. 19, list of subscribers to building fund; 1831, July 25, copy of agreement signed by members to subscribe specified sums of money for erecting a public library "to consist of book in which the Doctrines of the New Jerusalem Church are contained and taught, and also books in which those doctrines are questioned or disputed;" 1843, Oct. 10, deed, Lewis Beers to the First New Jerusalem Church of the County of Tioga (now Tompkins) land on which church was erected; undated, list of subscribers to purchase organ
- Jabez and Lewis Beers: New Jerusalem Church papers, n.d. (Box 2)
- Newspaper clippings: History of Ithaca and environs (Box 2)
- Tornado Hook & Ladder Co. #3 papers (probably originally collected by Dr. Coville), 1843-1928 (Box 2)
  Lists of members and attendance records, menus, announcements of meetings, a few letters of resignation, etc., record of men in Service, June 1, 1918, annual report for 1928, broadside (in broadside collection); 1843,Feb. 21, lady's ticket - First Annual Ball - Fire Co. #3; booklets: Articles of Incorporation, By-Laws, Rules of Order and Membership, Ithaca, 1887; photograph of painting of bucket brigade fighting blaze; copies of photographs of old fire engines
- Tornado Hook and Ladder Company papers, n.d. (Box 2)
- Elsbree Family papers, 1761-1951 (Box 2)
  Mimeographed family letters (1941-1951); typescript copy of statement of Nov. 15, 1933 regarding Ithaca Trust Co. as Trustee v. Ernest Blaker and Cascadilla School Association, and resultant payment of $8.04 to Estate of Phebe C. Elsbree, as bondholder; children's letters: Nathan Elsbree to Mother, July 4, 1887, one signed "Thomas," n.d. and another Llewelyn, both to their grandmother, n.d.; 2 postcards and letter to Anna E. from John? (cousin) (1942); typescript copy of will of Ephraim Elsbree, Jan. 3, 1761; 1872-1927 invitations
- Miscellaneous Papers, 1897-1941, n.d. (Box 2)
  Letter to Miss Curtis, June 7, 1926, from Adelaide Curtis Gunther; 2 undated and unsigned poems written longhand on fashions; Oct. 18, 1897, card to Prof. E. Hitchcock, Jr.; letter (March 2, 1932) and 4 postcards (1941) to a Mrs. Harry G. Morgan, Ithaca, from her daughter; typescript copy of letter of Oct. 1828 from Betsy Curtis to her aunt (?) describing ball at the (Yale?) commencement exercises, and commenting on family matters
- Tornado Hook and Ladder Co. No. 3, Ithaca, New York 1831-1931, 1931 (Box 2)
- Tornado Hook and Ladder Co. No. 3, Ithaca, New York, 1887 (Box 2)
- Tornado Hook and Ladder Co. No. 3, Ithaca, New York, 1831-1916, 1916 (Box 2)
- Outward Bound - A Journal and Note-Book for Ocean Voyages, kept by Elizabeth T. Curtis, S.S. Barbarossa, June 12, 1902, 1893 (Box 2)
- The Prime Ancient Society of Fairfield, Conn. 1639-1889, 1889 (Box 2)
- News Boy's Greetings Ithaca Dailly News, 1909 (Box 2)
- History of the Ely Re-union, held at Lyme, Conn., July 10th, 1878, 1878 (Box 2)
- "Act of Incorporation and Rules & Regulations of the Cornell Library Association, Ithaca, N.Y.", 1876 (Box 2)
- "Sermon on the Occasion of the Last Sunday in the Old (Christ) Church, Towanda, Penna., by Rev. Percy J. Robottom, M.A.", 1889 (Box 2)
- Reunion of the Descendants of Daniel Shelton, at Birmingham, Conn., June 14th, 1877, 1877 (Box 2)
- leaflet: The Little Chapel on the Mount, 1931 (Box 2)
- The Congregational Church of Danby, N.Y. Services to Commemorate the One Hundred and Twenty-fifth Anniversary of the Founding of the Church and the Thirty-eighth Year of the Pastorate of the Rev. B. F. Tobey, Oct. 2, 1932, 1932 (Box 2)
- Genealogical data - printed matter (Box 3)
- Genealogical notes - A-B (Box 3)
- Genealogical notes - C (Box 3)
- Genealogical notes - D-F (Box 3)
- Genealogical notes - G-Hall (Box 3)
- Genealogical notes - Hawes (Box 3)
- Genealogical notes - Hawkins-Hyatt (Box 3)
- Genealogical notes - J-K (Box 3)
- Genealogical notes - L-M (Box 3)
- Genealogical notes - P-S (Box 3)
- Genealogical notes - T-Z (Box 3)
- Genealogical notes - miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Scrapbook - newspaper clippings, c. 1872-1924; manuscript poems (Box 3)